Guide to the Educom records, 1963-1972
Duke University. University Archives
Educom records 1963-1972
Duke University. University Archives
Educom
3.75 linear feet Extent: 3750 Items
Educom (The Interuniversity Communications Council) was formed to provide universities an effective means of collaboration in their efforts to utilize the potential benefits of the emerging communications sciences for educational pursuits. Contains materials that reflect Duke University's membership in Educom and includes correspondence, Educom Bulletins, reports, and minutes. The collection ranges in date from 1963-1972.
UA.26.03.0011
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Educom records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1977.
Historical Note
The Interuniversity Communications Council (EDUCOM and INTERCOM) was organized in a preliminary fashion as a non-profit corporation at a meeting held in Denver, Colorado, in October 1964. Present at this meeting were academic officers of seven universities: Duke University, Harvard University, State University of New York, University of California, University of Michigan, University of Pittsburgh, and the University of Virginia. Its Board of Directors consisted of individuals chosen from among those proposed by institutional members and included a President, Vice President, Secretary, Treasurer, and Executive Director. A Scientific Advisory Board was also established and consisted of one representative from each member institution.
Educom was formed to keep universities informed of nationwide developments in the field of communications. Interests included the storage and retrieval of information, uses of computers in research and teaching, new methods of teaching and learning and data processing in universities. The specific objectives included developing new concepts, techniques, and applications of the communications sciences developed with increasing rapidity and establishing task forces in areas of critical development.
The first Educom conference was held at Duke University in 1966 with 150 in attendance. Educom's first president, Edison Montgomery of the University of Pittsburgh, was elected. William G. Anlyan, Duke University's Dean of the School of Medicine at the time, served as the first Chairman of the Board of Trustees from 1964-1969.
In 1998, an organization originally named the College and University Systems Exchange (CAUSE) disbanded and consolidated with Educom to form EDUCAUSE. Duke University remains an active member. For more information, please go to www.educause.edu.
Collection Overview
Contains materials that reflect Duke University's membership in Educom and includes correspondence, Educom Bulletins, reports, and minutes. The collection ranges in date from 1963-1972.
Subject Headings
Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Information sciences; Educom; Educom. Directories; Anlyan, William G.; Information and computing
Related Material
Library Administration Records, 1930-1998
Duke University Archives
Douglas M. Knight Records, 1949-1970
Duke University Archives
William G. Anlyan Papers, 1930-1995
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Nominating Committee, 1966 March 8 (Box 1)
  - Office of Naval Research, 1967 July 20 (Box 1)
  - Network for Triangle Area, 1966 September-October (Box 1)
  - National Science Foundation, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - National Meeting, Tallahassee, FL, 1967 March 15-16 (Box 1)
  - National Institutes of Health, 1967 March (Box 1)
  - National Environmental Health Sciences Center, 1966 June-July (Box 1)
  - Travel Expenses, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Montgomery, Edison, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Task Force Information Networks, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous: Brochures, correspondence, bio sketches, 1972 (Box 1)
  - EDUCOM: Report of the Summer Study on Information Networks, preliminary draft, 1966 September (Box 1)
  - EDUCOM: Research Report, Agricultural Sciences Information Network Development Plan, 1969 August (Box 1)
  - Organization and Personnel, Subcommittee on, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Presidency, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Publications, Miscellaneous, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Regan, Peter F., 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Releases, undated (Box 2)
  - Reports, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Reprints, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Summer Study, Study in Educational Communications Networks, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Summer Study Grant, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Task Forces, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Task Force, Computer-Based Clinical Operations, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Task Force, Continuing Education, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Task Force, Copyrights and Patents, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Task Force, Educational Systems and Technologies, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Periodical, Networks for Higher Education, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Spring Conference, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Annual Meeting, 1971 October (Box 2)
  - Fourth Annual Meeting, 1968 October 15-16 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Educational Communications, Duke University, 1966 April 13-15 (Box 3)
  - EDUCOM Bulletin, 1966-1972 (Box 3)
  - Advanced Research Project Agency, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Meeting, 1968 May 14-15 (Box 3)
  - Agenda, 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy, Inc. (AURA), 1957 (Box 3)
  - Associated Universities, Inc., 1964 (Box 3)
  - Baruch, Jordan, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Becker, Joseph, 1966-1968 (Box 3)
  - Benefits and Responsibilities, undated (Box 3)
  - Budget, 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - Computer-based Educational Systems, undated (Box 3)
  - Computer Printouts, 1963, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Copyright, 1968 (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1965-1972 (Box 3)
  - Anlyan, William G., 1964-1967 (Box 3)
  - Bylaws, Interuniversity Communications Council, Inc., 1964-1972 (Box 3)
  - Educom: Final Report, 1972 June (Box 3)
  - Diffusion of Computer Systems in Higher Education, Subcommittee on, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Directory, 1965-1967 (Box 4)
  - Dues, 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Educational Communications Networks, 1967 (Box 4)
  - EDUNET, 1966 (Box 4)
  - EIN Project, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
  - Financial Statements, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Ford Foundation, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
  - General Information, 1965-1967 (Box 4)
  - General Learning Corporation, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Goals and Objectives, Committee on, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Memorandum for Institutional and Trustee Representatives, 1968-1971 (Box 4)
  - IBM, undated (Box 4)
  - Instructional Television, Subcommittee on, 1967 (Box 4)
  - INTRACOM, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Annual Report to the Kellogg Foundation, 1967 June 8 (Box 4)
  - Kellogg Grant, 1965-1967 (Box 4)
  - Member Universities, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
  - History, 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1967-1970 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1964-1966 (Box 5)
  - Mental Retardation, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Miller, James G., 1965-1968 (Box 5)
  - Missouri, University of, 1967 (Box 5)